<MedlineCitation Status="Completed">
<MedlineID>10011135</MedlineID>
<PMID>420699</PMID>
<DateCreated>
<Year>1979</Year>
<Month>04</Month>
<Day>28</Day>
</DateCreated>
<DateCompleted>
<Year>1979</Year>
<Month>04</Month>
<Day>28</Day>
</DateCompleted>
<DateRevised>
<Year>2000</Year>
<Month>12</Month>
<Day>18</Day>
</DateRevised>
<Article>
<Journal>
<ISSN>0067-8147</ISSN>
<JournalIssue>
<Issue>159</Issue>
<PubDate>
<Year>1979</Year>
</PubDate>
</JournalIssue>
</Journal>
<ArticleTitle>The understanding and teaching of reaction to pain.</ArticleTitle>
<Pagination>
<MedlinePgn>114-40</MedlinePgn>
</Pagination>
<Abstract>
<AbstractText>Pain is both the commonest and one of the most enigmatic symptoms in medicine. Its subjective nature renders management difficult and its conceptualization is complex. Reaction to pain cannot be easily generalized; group differences are postulated, based on sex, age, culture, psychiatric diagnosis and personality variables. Early developmental aspects of pain and discussed in animal studies and case reports but little systematic data exist. Experimental findings show the influence on pain response of cognitive and emotional factors. Clinically, the variables determining perception, reporting and reaction to pain are numerous and harder to study scientifically. Acute and chronic pain should be distinguished: the latter is more complicated, leading of ten to diagnostic problems and management stalemates. Discovering the relationship of pain to emotional phenomena, as cause or effect, is difficult, though essential to effective treatment. Various frames of reference apply: e.g., individual medical, familial, and "workmen's compensation" models. Reaction by family, lawyer, or work commission involves potential secondary gain and may reinforce or discourage pathological responses by the patient. The potential of pain for symbolic meaning and its acceptance as a "legitimate" medical symptom renders it ideal for both expression and masquerading of intrapsychic and interpersonal conflicts involving anger, punishment, control and dependency. Teaching about pain and its significance is best done in clinical settings such as obstetrical units and multidisciplinary pain clinics. Videotaped modular presentations with discussion provide a satisfactory though less desirable alternative.</AbstractText>
</Abstract>
<AuthorList>
<Author>
<LastName>Ramsay</LastName>
<ForeName>R A</ForeName>
<Initials>RA</Initials>
</Author>
</AuthorList>
<Language>eng</Language>
<PublicationTypeList>
<PublicationType>Journal Article</PublicationType>
</PublicationTypeList>
</Article>
<MedlineJournalInfo>
<Country>SWITZERLAND</Country>
<MedlineTA>Bibl Psychiatr</MedlineTA>
<NlmUniqueID>0255452</NlmUniqueID>
</MedlineJournalInfo>
<CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset>
<MeshHeadingList>
<MeshHeading>
<DescriptorName>Acute Disease</DescriptorName>
</MeshHeading>
<MeshHeading>
<DescriptorName>Age Factors</DescriptorName>
</MeshHeading>
<MeshHeading>
<DescriptorName>Chronic Disease</DescriptorName>
</MeshHeading>
<MeshHeading>
<DescriptorName>Cognition</DescriptorName>
</MeshHeading>
<MeshHeading>
<DescriptorName>Culture</DescriptorName>
</MeshHeading>
<MeshHeading>
<DescriptorName>Education, Medical</DescriptorName>
</MeshHeading>
<MeshHeading>
<DescriptorName>Emotions</DescriptorName>
</MeshHeading>
<MeshHeading>
<DescriptorName>Human</DescriptorName>
</MeshHeading>
<MeshHeading>
<DescriptorName>Pain</DescriptorName>
<QualifierName MajorTopicYN="Y">psychology</QualifierName>
</MeshHeading>
<MeshHeading>
<DescriptorName>Perception</DescriptorName>
</MeshHeading>
<MeshHeading>
<DescriptorName>Personality</DescriptorName>
</MeshHeading>
<MeshHeading>
<DescriptorName>Sex Factors</DescriptorName>
</MeshHeading>
</MeshHeadingList>
</MedlineCitation>
